[Music]
it's July 10 2023 this is Daniel
Friedman from the active inference
Institute I'm just going to give an
example usage of a few things that we
did today at the Active inference
journal with the chat GPT code
interpreter functionality
so for a little bit of context the
active inference Journal picks up where
the live streams leave off we do speech
to text language processing manual
automated curation integrating language
models always working on publishing
pipelines open science and as soon as we
saw that we had access to the code
interpreter today one thought was to
head over to our live stream organizing
full data which has a bunch of
information on the dates times types of
streams guests title of the stream
number of the stream any Associated
papers and some other information and we
wanted to analyze this information and
just get some descriptive statistics and
also take it in a few different
directions and see where we could go
with it so here in coda.io table options
three dots on the upper right downloaded
it as a CSV and then brought it in to
chat GPT for code interpreter so I began
by asking it to to be an expert code
interpreter and then ask for some
visualizations by uploading this CSV
that had been downloaded from our
previous coded page
some description
along with a code was provided
we started with some word cloud
visualizations now maybe not the exact
visualization that one would want but
could always fine tune it so an
incredible first start
different guests
a little bit of a
chart needing some tuning but again
downloadable presented with code
I asked for a principal component
analysis
and it brought up a uh suggestion about
one hot encoding
but also the caveat that that might not
yield meaningful results
I said go for it however you see best
the code was provided
a PCA was downloadable
I asked for some information about the
semantic loading of what those principal
components were associated with
and some caveats and opportunities were
raised I I asked for
the
language model to just proceed with
whatever visualization it thought was
best
made a heat map
however unknown
has the highest frequency
and so I asked for the heat map to be
re-visualized without the unknown column
and that gave us a lot finer resolution
to see which guests were repeatedly in
which different live stream series
[Music]
I asked about which guests are most
strongly associated with which streams
and to ask for visualization
bar chart was displayed of different
guests here with colors across by
different
types of streams
asked for a word cloud of the topics of
their streams
and the code was provided
here in the initial word clouds it only
used the type of the Stream So for Chris
fields we had his course information
physics is information processing for
avell we had the ongoing course active
inference for the social sciences
for Andrew who's the course assistant
for Chris fields we saw the same
information as Chris fields
and for Maxwell who had only ever joined
for live streaming guest stream this was
most associated worked
these terms were downloaded and I asked
for them to be output more directly
again this kind of sparse
um cloud
and so I asked for a correction the word
cloud should be person specific and
based upon the titles of streams they
are in
that's what we discussed not the stream
series
and so this actually did bring in for
some
fields
some of those
topics that were discussed
I asked for some general statistical
comparisons on the data
it brought up that a chi-square might be
a better first option
I said go for doing as many chi-squares
as your heart desires
it shows the code from scipy for
chi-squared tests
and
with a p-value
that's in the negative 150 second order
of magnitude we have an association
between series and guests unsurprising
then I took things in a little different
direction
and asked for a comprehensive
professional PhD dissertation
integrating all the information above
this PhD dissertation proposal
was very focused on using live stream
data to approach the research process
and quite a general scale
so it was actually a bit too General
because I was looking for something a
bit more particular even though this was
a great nine chapter proposal
so I asked for a more technical
dissertation that focuses on the
theoretical and practical aspects of
active inference in the free energy
principle
and so this got a lot closer to where I
want to be
investigating patterns and Dynamics and
live stream data through the lens of
active inference and the free energy
principle
and so here we begin with some
situational awareness around live
streaming as a rapidly growing phenomena
and begin to introduce the topic and the
reasons why live stream data are useful
or at least give us a useful perspective
to swap into about active inference
some interesting sections so definitely
a lot of uh areas for future work
but natural language is not all and this
visualization capacity looked really
powerful so I asked for a graphical
abstract for that dissertation as a PNG
in the browser to make sure that it was
going to be visible and not just
downloadable so here we see a really
meta word cloud analysis
in fact this is a simple word cloud
but nice kind of summaries of the
chapters would be good for presentations
I asked to make a Bayesian graph that
visualizes the core ideas and claims of
the dissertation
in this graph blue nodes represent the
main inputs
orange nodes represent the analytical
methods used
word cloud analysis PC analysis
co-occurrence analysis chi-square test
so here we have these four analytical
methods
being used in relationship to free
energy principle octave inference and
live stream data
all of it combining into the green node
with the findings
I asked for this Bayesian graph to be
re-rendered using the motifs of
cybernetic systems like input output
relationships semantic information flows
and hierarchical metacognitive nesting
and a slightly rearranged graph was
displayed
in an updated graph live stream data is
positioned at the top as the primary
input to the system
active inference and free energy
principle nodes are positioned at the
same level representing parallel
foundational Concepts
the analytical methods are positioned in
the middle representing the processing
or transformation layer of the system
the findings node is positioned at the
bottom
as the output of the system
the arrows represent semantic
information flows with the direction of
the arrow indicating the flow of
information or influence
the graph illustrates the hierarchical
nesting of the system and highlights the
input output relationships and flow of
information
so I asked write an agent-based modeling
framework of a sophisticated cognitive
agent that engages in epistemic activity
sufficient to generate the kinds of
patterns discussed All Above
and qualitatively in agent-based
modeling framework was provided
agent definition
environment definition
active inference in the free energy
principle
good poor strained
communication of the active inference
ontology
generation of patterns
and of course
I went next to the visualizations
and have so many more directions that
are probably really fruitful for you and
I to explore
but alas
I reached my current usage cap for gpt4
I can continue with the default model
now or try again in about an hour
so I thought I'd make this nice summary
video because even just on a first run
this has been highly
interesting
and I welcome everyone who wants to
explore and learn more to get involved
at the Active inference Institute or
check out what we're up to in the
journal here's some next steps to kind
of present themselves following this
video
to characterize our Journal process and
improve our visualization automation
editing so we have a multi-step process
of the journal that helps us
go from a YouTube live stream on through
the audio and markdown editing to
translation and rendering and Publishing
so how can we improve this and how can
we work better in language translations
and subtitles how can we integrate
language models and Transformer models
how can we
input process and output markdown files
better
how can we integrate with DOI digital
object identifier and DSi publishing
affordances we already do this through
GitHub and zenodo but maybe there's some
other ways that we could get some
publishing affordances going
and uh yeah we'll look forward to
how things develop in this area
and again there's a lot of ways to get
involved at the journal if anything that
we've discussed if any of the topics or
the live streams are interesting to you
and you want to get involved at the
journal where we archive and curate and
improve those transcripts make them part
of the citable discourse then we're
looking forward to hearing from you so
bye